{"tossups": [{"question": "This woman was thought to be a boy just after birth because she was \u201chairy\u201d and cried with a \u201cstrong, hoarse voice\u201d, prompting her father to say \"She'll be clever, she has made fools of us all!\" upon learning her true sex. This woman aroused controversy while visiting the French court when she had Gian Rinaldo Monaldeschi stabbed to death for treason. After winning the Torstenson War, this ruler\u2019s country was granted exemption from the (*) Sound Dues. She founded the Amaranten Order of knights and required that they not marry, reflecting her own decision not to do so. This woman authorized the settlement of New Sweden and was advised by Axel Oxenstierna. Known for employing Descartes, for 10 points, name this daughter of Gustavus Adolphus and queen of Sweden.", "answer": "Queen Christina of Sweden or Christina Vasa", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Queen Christina of Sweden or Christina Vasa</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Queen Christina of Sweden or Christina Vasa"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The original manuscript for the founding text of the modern form of this discipline was erroneously claimed to have been lost to a fire during a riot in 2011. Ibn Wahshiyya\u2019s work in this discipline was influential on later scholars in the same field like Athanasius Kircher and Silvestre de Sacy. Cheikh Anta Diop was a critic of the early 20th century Dynastic Race theory in this discipline. The writings of Immanuel Velikovsky influenced the Glasgow (*) Chronology, a generally rejected paradigm in this discipline. This discipline\u2019s modern form began with Napoleon\u2019s invasion of the namesake country and was studied archaeologically by Flinders Petrie and Howard Carter. For 10 points, name this interdisciplinary field that studies the history and culture of an ancient civilization along the Nile.", "answer": "Egyptology (accept more specific answers that specify that it\u2019s ancient Egypt being studied; prompt on things like archaeology, philology, history, etc.)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Egyptology</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Egyptology"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept more specific answers that specify that it\u2019s ancient Egypt being studied; prompt on things like archaeology, philology, history, etc."}, {"question": "This kingdom was legendarily founded by a woman who floated to China on a piece of sandalwood and married a Chinese prince, but after returning to her homeland, she turned that prince and his fleet to stone when the prince tried to bring her back to China. This kingdom developed from the Sa Hu\u1ef3nh culture, notable for its region for using iron more than bronze. This kingdom moved its capital from Indrapura to Vijaya after an invasion from the north, and refugees from that invasion were the progenitors of the Utsul people of Hainan. This kingdom\u2019s final powerful ruler was Che Bunga, the \u201cRed King\u201d, after whose reign this kingdom was slowly whittled down by attacks from the (*) \u0110\u1ea1i Vi\u1ec7t. For 10 points, name this Hindu kingdom of southern Vietnam.", "answer": "Champa Kingdom", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Champa Kingdom</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Champa Kingdom"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In 2014, a gold object with this man\u2019s name on it, the Curmsun Disc, was donated to a museum in Sweden, over 150 years since its discovery in Poland. Until 1977, this man was believed to have ordered the death of a woman found in a bog who was thought to be Gunnhild, Mother of Kings. In one account, this man converted to Christianity when the priest Poppa carried \u201ca great weight\u201d of heated iron without being burned. This ruler was captured by the possibly fictional Styrbj\u00f6rn the Strong. This king built five forts surrounding his capital at (*) Aarhus at places like Nonnebakken and Trelleborg. Like his father, this man erected rune-covered stones at Jelling. For 10 points, name this son of Gorm the Old and father of Sveyn Forkbeard, the first Christian king of Denmark.", "answer": "Harald Bluetooth (accept Harald Gormsson before Gorm is mentioned)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Harald Bluetooth</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Harald Bluetooth"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Harald Gormsson before Gorm is mentioned"}, {"question": "An outpost established for this activity was the most famous place to be run by an official called an Opperhoofd. It did not involve Brazil, but King Sebastian of Portugal decried the acquisition of slaves due to this activity because he believed it would hurt missionary activity. The wreck of the San Felipe revealed an alleged Spanish invasion, threatening this activity and leading to the crucifixion of (*) 26 Christians. In order to keep up scientifically with a people called K\u014dm\u014d, an extended cessation of this activity prompted the study of rangaku. This activity ended with the adoption of the Sakoku policy and the restriction of European contact to Dejima Island. For 10 points, identify this activity naming a 16th century historical period and known in Japanese by a name meaning \u201csouthern barbarian\u201d.", "answer": "Nanban trade (accept descriptive answers suggesting trade between Europe and Japan before \u201cEuropean\u201d)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Nanban trade</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Nanban trade"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept descriptive answers suggesting trade between Europe and Japan before \u201cEuropean\u201d"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s cat Trim fell off the HMS Reliance as a kitten, but got itself back on board by climbing a rope, and now has a statue alongside its master in his hometown. This man was held prisoner for 6 years on Mauritius by Charles Decaen because his country was at war with France. This man\u2019s meeting with Nicolas Baudin gave Encounter Bay its name. This explorer was a member of William Bligh\u2019s Second Breadfruit Voyage that successfully brought the crop to the Caribbean. This explorer was the first to give (*) New Holland its modern appellation. This man achieved his most famous accomplishment when he sailed west from the Gulf of Carpentaria to repair his ship in Sydney. For 10 points, identify this English explorer, the first person to circumnavigate Australia.", "answer": "Matthew Flinders", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Matthew Flinders</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Matthew Flinders"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Legends of this people tell of much of the southern extent of their homeland being lost under the ocean and a 20th century revival movement has given that land a name emphasizing its \u201cpurity\u201d as the cradle of civilization. Some of the earliest love poetry of this people was written within a framework of five landscapes that mirrored various qualities of the romantic relationship. Several invasions from the Khilji dynasty destroyed a kingdom of this people in the early 14th century and led to the creation of a namesake sultanate in their former capital of (*) Madurai. A kingdom of this people expanded its influence into SE Asia after raiding ports like Kedah and Palembang of the Srivijaya Kingdom. The most famous kingdom ruled by this people was ruled by several rulers named Rajendra and Rajaraja. For 10 points, name this Dravidian people of South India and Sri Lanka who ruled the Pandya and Chola dynasties.", "answer": "Tamil people (prompt on Dravidian people) \u00a0", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Tamil people</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Tamil people"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on Dravidian people"}, {"question": "The completion of a trial of a member of this family was announced to the public by the erection of a red gallows at Byt\u010da (\u201cbeet-chah\u201d). This family was the most notable branch of the Gutkeled clan. The highest post achieved by a member of this family was only gained because Henry III of France refused it. After his country was successful at the Battle of Wenden, that same man of this family initiated a military campaign which took Polotsk and Velikiye Luki. The most infamous member of this house was imprisoned in (*) Csejte (\u201cchay-teh\u201d) Castle for killing dozens of young women and apocryphally bathing in their blood. For 10 points, this is which Hungarian noble family to which belonged de uxoris King of Poland Stephen and Elizabeth, the \u201cBlood Countess\u201d?", "answer": "B\u00e1thory family", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>B\u00e1thory family</u></b>", "acceptable": ["B\u00e1thory family"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "71 year old lawyer Yusuf al-Findalawi fought and died while defending this city during a siege. A state centered on this city reached its peak under Hazael, who, on the Tel Dan Stele, recorded the first known non-Biblical reference to King David. Abdelkader el Djezairi protected many Christians in his home during the 1860 massacre of Christians in this city, for which Abraham Lincoln sent him a pair of pistols. One section of this city was renamed al-Hariqa, or \u201cthe fire\u201d, after it was burned during a French bombing campaign. This city\u2019s largest mosque is dedicated to (*) St. John the Baptist and supposedly contains his head. The 1148 siege of this city was broken by Nur ad-Din and ended the Second Crusade. For 10 points, name this capital of the Umayyad Caliphate and modern Syria.", "answer": "Damascus", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Damascus</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Damascus"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The founder of this institution invoked Saints Peter and Paul to curse anyone who broke its charter. This institution was built in three distinct phases; the second began after a Hungarian raid and the third was financed by a massive donation from Ferdinand I of Le\u00f3n. One leader of this place, Peter the Venerable, was part of the team that created the first Latin translation of the Qur\u2019an. Cardinals (*) Richelieu and Mazarin both led this institution while serving as ministers to the kings of France. This institution is most famous for its precedent of specifically mandating secular non-interference in its affairs, soon followed by monasteries across Europe. For 10 points, this is what influential Burgundian monastery, the namesake of a 10th century reform movement?", "answer": "Cluny Abbey", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Cluny Abbey</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Cluny Abbey"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Some unsubstantiated early European accounts of this commodity claim that it was sometimes gathered by pestering monkeys who would then collect this commodity and throw it at the people bothering them. One legend claims that this commodity first grew on the spot where Bodhidharma cut off his own eyelids in rage for having fallen asleep after nine years of meditation. The brothers Charles and Robert Bruce were instrumental in the first expansion of the area of production of this commodity after discovering its use by the natives of (*) Assam. The Kissa Y\u014dj\u014dki is the first Japanese text specifically on this commodity and was written by Eisai, the Zen monk who first brought its cultivation to Japan from China. Apocryphally discovered by Emperor Shennong when its leaves fell into his cup of boiling water, for 10 points, identify this beverage that comes in green and black varieties.", "answer": "tea", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>tea</u></b>", "acceptable": ["tea"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This man served as Professor of Military Science and Tactics at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln for four years, during which time he formed a highly successful drill team. This general was called \u201ccool as a bowl of cracked ice\u201d while fighting at San Juan Hill. In one campaign, this leader oversaw the creation of an improved boot to relieve his soldier\u2019s foot problems. One of this general\u2019s most famous expeditions was the first to use a truck supply convoy and the target of that expedition was later given a house in (*) Chihuahua by his government. This man received his nickname for leading the 10th Cavalry Regiment, a unit of Buffalo Soldiers. For 10 points, name this general who captured Pancho Villa and led the American Expeditionary Forces in WWI.", "answer": "John \u201cBlack Jack\u201d Pershing", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>John \u201cBlack Jack\u201d Pershing</u></b>", "acceptable": ["John \u201cBlack Jack\u201d Pershing"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One of these objects found at Chehrabad provides the earliest evidence for intestinal parasites in Iran. The M\u0101ori created partial examples of these objects called mokomakai that were often displayed on marae. A type of brown paint popular among the Pre-Raphaelites was created partially from these objects and Edward Burne-Jones buried his supply of that paint when he learned that these objects were used in its creation. A means of creating these objects in Japan was called sokushinbutsu and part of the process involved only eating seeds and pine needles. A notable one of these objects was found high in the Alps north of Bolzano and has been given the name (*) \u00d6tzi. For 10 points, identify these objects created from the natural or artificial desiccation of human or animal remains of which King Tut is the most famous.", "answer": "mummies (accept equivalents)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>mummies</u></b>", "acceptable": ["mummies"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept equivalents"}, {"question": "A suburb of this city contains a memorial to the Polish destroyer Piorun, which helped defend this city during an air raid. The Bridgeton Billy Boys and the Norman Conks were two of the most famous of this city\u2019s \u201crazor gangs\u201d in the 1920-1930\u2019s. The 1945 Bruce Report was an influential proposal for urban and economic renewal in this city. The area of this city now called Merchant City was so named for the lavish mansions the (*) Tobacco Lords built here. The economy of this center for the import of American tobacco grew rapidly following the late 18th century de-silting of the River Clyde, after which it became a textile and shipbuilding center of Scotland. For 10 points, identify this most populous city of Scotland.", "answer": "Glasgow", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Glasgow</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Glasgow"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A ruler of this kingdom is denied having killed an enemy prince in single combat by that enemy\u2019s accounts, which claim that that prince died from mortar fire while trying to kill a rampaging elephant. Commoners in this kingdom were obligated to register themselves for corv\u00e9e labor under leaders called nais, but were able to sell themselves to new masters. Yamada Nagamasa led a Japanese trading colony in this kingdom in the early 17th century and supposedly buried a cache of treasure in eastern Australia. A 1688 siege of a port city in this kingdom led to the death of (*) Constantine Phaulkon, a Greek advisor to King Narai. A Burmese invasion led by Mingyi Swa was repulsed by King Naresuan and saw those leaders fight in single combat on elephant-back. For 10 points, what was this Thai kingdom of the 14th-18th centuries with a similar-sounding name to the birthplace of Rama?", "answer": "Ayutthaya Kingdom (prompt on Siam)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Ayutthaya Kingdom</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Ayutthaya Kingdom"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on Siam"}, {"question": "This city experienced such bad smog one day in 1939 that streetlights were needed all day. This city\u2019s United Welfare Association successfully campaigned for segregated housing districts, resulting in no one being permitted to live on a block with 75% people of another race. Because it mostly displaced African-Americans, the NAACP called the Mill Creek Valley neighborhood in this city a \u201cNegro Removal Project\u201d. This city\u2019s mid-20th century attempt at (*) urban renewal resulted in several squalid, crime-ridden housing projects, including the particularly awful Pruitt-Igoe complex. The replacement stadium for the decaying Sportsman\u2019s Park destroyed this city\u2019s Chinatown. For 10 points, name this home of Busch Stadium and the largest city of Missouri.", "answer": "St. Louis", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>St. Louis</u></b>", "acceptable": ["St. Louis"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A ruler of a kingdom in this region allegedly used his 500 wives to spy on his subordinates and his cursed, decapitated head supposedly led to the death of a Canadian military officer. The southernmost portion of this region was given to its colonial ruler so that it could access the big game of the Bangweula Wetlands in an agreement mediated by Umberto I. The Yeke Kingdom was centered in this region and was formed by King Msiri. The Benguela Railroad was constructed to link this region to the coast. A (*) breakaway state in this region was governed by the CONAKAT party. Patrice Lumumba was killed in this region\u2019s capital Lubumbashi in 1961. For 10 points, what is this region of the southern DRC that was briefly independent in the \u201860\u2019s under Moise Tshombe?", "answer": "Katanga", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Katanga</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Katanga"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A colonial era fort in this city was given the name Fort Sensible after its garrison once gave up their commander per the demands of an attacking force. This city\u2019s founding was commemorated with the planting of a lemon tree, the sweetest fruit available at the time. The founder of this town attempted to rob and murder George Washington and had a silver prosthetic tongue. A prohibition law in this city passed 200 years ago was briefly re-enforced before it was learned that it was repealed (*) 199 years ago. This city began Whacking Day in the early 20th century as an excuse to beat up Irish immigrants. This city\u2019s founder split with Shelbyville Manhattan over the right to marry one\u2019s cousins, leading to the current enmity between their respective towns, and was once a pirate by the name of Hans Sprungfeld. For 10 points, what is this city, the home of the Simpsons?", "answer": "Springfield", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Springfield</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Springfield"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The capture of cities like Ephesos and Sardis by Prepelaus occurred during the campaign leading to this battle. One kingdom participating in this battle was raided by a kingdom to the south as far north as Sidon, an action that was broken off due to rumors that this battle had already occurred. After this battle, the population of the loser\u2019s capital, a city named after him, was removed to Antioch. The deciding maneuver in this battle was the separation of the loser\u2019s cavalry from their main force by Seleucus\u2019 (*) elephants. Following this battle, Demetrius, the son of the losing commander, established himself as ruler of Macedonia. For 10 points, what was this 301 BCE battle that saw Seleucus I, Cassander, and Lysimachus ally against Antigonus I Monophthalamos, which ended Antigonid rule in Asia and any hope of reviving Alexander\u2019s empire?", "answer": "Battle of Ipsus", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Battle of Ipsus</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Battle of Ipsus"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In the 17th century, this city was home to the badass swordswomen, lesbian lovers, and possible vigilantes Ana Lezama de Urinza and Do\u00f1a Eustaquia de Sonza, now known as the \u201cValiant Women of [this city]\u201d. A mountain outside this city is supposedly inhabited by the malevolent spirit El T\u00edo. Slaves called ac\u00e9milas humanas, or \u201chuman mules\u201d, were used to conduct this city\u2019s most important craft after the death of the original, actual mules. The development of the (*) patio process was integral in the economy of this place, with Huancavelica, Peru providing most of the needed mercury. This city\u2019s vast mineral wealth was used to fund conquests in Chile and the much of the rest was used to pay for imports from China. For 10 points, identify this Bolivian city next to the Cerro Rico, which provided most of the Spanish Empire\u2019s silver.", "category": "History"}], "bonuses": []}